MINNESOTA TERRITORIAL ARCHIVES. Territorial Governor:
Series Records of territorial governor Willis A. Gorman,
1852-1857.
Minnesota Historical Society
Agency:Minnesota. Governor (1853-1857: Gorman).
Subject files, correspondence, appointments, pardon records, reports from territorial officers, requests for return of fugitives, and miscellany.
0.75 cu. ft. (23 folders in 2 partial boxes).
BIOGRAPHICAL SKETCH OF GOVERNOR WILLIS A. GORMAN
Willis Arnold Gorman was born in Kentucky on January 12, 1816. His early career was as a lawyer and state legislator (Democrat) in Indiana. During the Mexican War he raised and commanded an Indiana rifle battalion and an infantry regiment, and subsequently was elected to two terms in the U.S. Congress. President Franklin Pierce appointed him Governor of Minnesota in May 13, 1853, and he served in that office until 1857. He was subsequently a delegate to the state constitutional convention (1857) and was elected to the first state legislature (1858).
At the outset of the Civil War he commanded the First Minnesota Infantry Volunteers (April-October, 1861) until his promotion to brigadier general. Following his discharge from military service in 1864, he practiced law in St. Paul in partnership with Cushman K. Davis. In 1869 he was appointed St. Paul city attorney, and held that office until his death on May 20, 1876.
Sources: Minnesota Biographies, pp. 267- 268; Minnesota in the Civil and Indian Wars, Vol. I, p. 14; William Watts Folwell, A History of Minnesota (St. Paul, rev. 1956), Vol. I, pp. 377-383; Theodore C. Blegen, Minnesota, A History of the State (1963), pp. 171, 240-242, 293.
SCOPE AND CONTENTS OF THE RECORDS
Subject files and correspondence of territorial governor Gorman. A large proportion relate to territorial officers' appointments and commissions. Letters received and sent address the following topics: concerns of federal civilian agencies, military and Indian affairs in general, the 1855 treaty with the Winnebago Indians, land sales, the Minnesota and Northwestern Railroad Company, and other territorial affairs. Also present are a legislative diary (Jan. 27-March 6, 1857), pardon records, petitions regarding local government organization, reports from territorial officers, and requests from other states for return of fugitives.
Gorman's governorship spanned a period of both tangible and speculative growth in the state's infrastructure and economy, with numerous railroads, educational institutions, and corporations being chartered, new counties established, new towns incorporated, and several Indian treaties ratified. The surviving records contain only sketchy information on these developments, and do not appear to contain any significant documentation on an abortive 1857 scheme to remove the state capital from St. Paul to St. Peter.
ARRANGEMENT OF THE RECORDS
Arranged alphabetically by topic; thereunder chronologically within each folder.
INDEX TERMS
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the catalog of the Minnesota Historical Society. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Topics:
Civil-military relations--Minnesota.; Extraditions--Minnesota.; Federal government--Minnesota.; Indians of North America—Government relations--1789-1869.; Land titles--Minnesota--Registration and transfer.; Pardons--Minnesota.; Winnebago Indians--Treaties.
Places:
Minnesota--Officials and employees--Selection and appointment.; Minnesota--Politics and government--1849-1858.
Persons:
Gorman, Willis Arnold, 1816-1876.
Organizations:
Minnesota Territory.
Types of Documents:
Diaries--Minnesota.; Petitions--Minnesota.; Proclamations--Minnesota.; Territorial records--Minnesota.
Accession Information:
Accession number(s): none; 2001-46
DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE RECORDS
Note to Researchers: To request materials, please note both the location and box numbers shown below.
- Appointments: Commission of Deeds, 1853-1857.; 1 folder. ([1])
  For each individual, may include any of the following: application, petition, recommendations, letter of resignation.
- Appointments: Counties, 1853-1857.; 1 folder.
  For each individual, may include any of the following: application, petition, recommendations, letter of resignation. Arranged alphabetically by county.
- Appointments: Notary Public, undated and 1853-1857.; 4 folders.
- Appointments: Territorial Offices, 1853-1857.
  May include any of the following: application, petition, recommendations, letter of resignation, for commissioner of emigration, librarian, superintendent of common schools, auditor, treasurer, building commissioner, supreme court reporter, militia, and land office.
- Commissions, 1855-1857.; 5 items.
  For notary public, justice of the peace, and building commissioner.
- Document Transmittals, Receipts, and Requests, 1853-1857.; 1 folder.
- Legislative Diary, 1, 1857.; 1 volume
  Fragmentary entries, January 27 - March 6, showing numbers and titles of bills.
- Letters Received: Federal Civilian Agencies, 18, 1853-1857.; 1 folder.
  Letters and circulars from federal civilian agencies, including the General Land Office, the Post Office Department, and the Treasury Department.
- Letters Received: Indian and Military Affairs, 1853-1857.; 1 folder. ([1])
  Letters, reports, and orders relating to Indian and military affairs, from the commanding officers at Fort Snelling and Fort Ridgely; from legislative district representatives about the Winnebago treaty, with a copy of Governor Gorman's reply (January 1854); and petitions and requests for defense against the Indians.
  Includes a letter written by Henry B. Smythe on behalf of the Winnebago Indians (8 Jan. 1856) requesting the transfer of $806 from tribal funds to the superintendent of the Winnebago School. It may refer to funds available to the tribe under the 1855 U.S. Treaty with the Winnebago; it is signed by many of the Winnebago signatories to that treaty.
- Letters Received: Land Sales, 1853-1857.; 9 items.
  Letters about land sales and occupancy.
- Letters Received: Other Territorial Affairs, 1853-1857.; 16 items.
  Letters from Senator Henry M. Rice and others about a variety of territorial affairs.
- Pardon Records, 1852-1857.; 21 items. ([2])
  Requests and petitions for pardons and commutations; governor's pardon; orders for release and related court records; letters for persons convicted and sentenced for various offenses, including murder, assault with intent to kill, assault and battery, simple assault, and resisting an officer; and letters asking for the release of an Indian hostage.
- Petitions, 1853-1855.; 10 items.
  Various requests and petitions for the establishment of election precincts in Portsmouth and the Sioux Agency, for the organization of local governments in Rice County and Steele County, for a town organization in Bangor, for a vigilance committee to suppress liquor traffic at Traverse des Sioux, and for a certification of election districts in Carver County.
- Proclamations, 1854-1855.; 2 items.
  Designating November 21, 1854, and November 20, 1855 as days of Thanksgiving.
- Records Relating to the Minnesota and Northwestern Railroad Company, 1854-1856.; 31 items.
  Bills, correspondence, and reports dealing with its incorporation and with the political maneuverings surrounding its proposed land grant.
- Reports: Board of Inspectors of the Territorial Prison, 1853-1856.; 1 folder. ([2])
  Reports that include activities of the board and minutes of board meetings.
- Reports: Commissioner of Emigration, 1854-1857.; 1 folder.
  Reports of activities, and financial reports including lists of expenditures and various receipts.
- Reports: Other Territorial Officers, 1853-1855.; 7 items.
  - - Agent to select university lands (December 12, 1855).
  - - Commissioner for the Crystal Palace Exhibition (1853, 1854).
  - - Superintendent of common schools (December 25, 1854).
  - - Territorial auditor (December 30, 1854; December 26, 1855).
- Requests for Return of Fugitives, 1854-1857.; 2 folders.
  Both to and from various states.